Guide to the Yale School of Architecture Building Project Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Yale School of Architecture Building Project records
1967-2008
RU 1078
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
16.5
11 boxes
41861.12
The materials consist of photographs, drawings, specifications, slides, negatives, publications, and publicity materials documenting the Yale School of Architecture's annual building project.
Yale University. School of Architecture
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 19-E (YRG 19-E), Records of departments, offices, programs, and projects of the Yale School of Architecture.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were transferred from the School of Architecture, 2008; gift of Paul Brouard, 2010.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.
Biographical / Historical
Since 1967, the Yale School of Architecture has offered its first-year students the unique chance to design and build a structure as part of their graduate education. Unique among architecture schools, this program is mandatory for all members of the class. Undertaken in cooperation with Common Ground, a local nonprofit agency, the Building Project results in a single-family house in an economically depressed neighborhood.
The late Charles W. Moore, who headed Yale's Department of Architecture (later the School of Architecture) from 1965 to 1971, founded the First-year Building Project in collaboration with faculty member Kent Bloomer. Moore saw that getting out of the studio and building something would have several benefits for the students. As a believer in simple tectonics and basic technologies, he hoped students would be inspired by the mechanics of building. In the midst of the student unrest of the 1960s he saw the project as a way for students to commit to positive social action by building for the poor.
The earliest projects were outside of New Haven, and included community centers in Appalachia and a series of camp buildings in Connecticut. Reduced budgets in the 1970s and 80s, as well as increasing pressure on student schedules, led to a scaling back of the program and projects-which included several park pavilions-were confined to the New Haven area.
More recently, partnerships with Habitat for Humanity and Home, Inc., Neighborhood Housing, and currently Common Ground, have led to a focus on affordable housing. The houses allow students the experience of working with a client and the opportunity to respond to the challenges of affordable housing and urban infill. Students have shown great enthusiasm for these projects focusing on community development and neighborhood improvement. Many of them arrive at school with a desire to include such socially responsible work in their future professional lives. Having the opportunity to participate in the design and construction of such building projects often reinforces their conviction and inspiration to do so.
from the Yale School of Architecture Building Project Website, 2010
Scope and Contents
The materials consist of photographs, drawings, specifications, slides, negatives, publications, and publicity materials documenting the Yale School of Architecture's annual building project.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged by accession.
Architecture -- Study and teaching (Graduate); Architecture; Public architecture -- Connecticut; Photographs; Yale University. School of Architecture and Design; Yale University. School of Architecture; Yale University. School of Art and Architecture
- Photographs, 1967-2006; Accession 2008-A-171; 3 linear feet and 41861.12 megabytes
  Conditions Governing Access
  The materials are open for research.
  - The Yale Building Project: A Resource Manual, circa 1997 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Color copies, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, 1993-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Negatives (color and black & white, 4x5), 1990s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Unused images, 1990s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Joseph Slifka Center plans, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Selected images, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Construction, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Reception, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Selected images, 1980s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Construction contact sheets, circa 1994 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 5x7 photographs: construction, models, completed buildings, 1982-1995 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Guilford Beach: articles collected by Nona and Kent Bloomer, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Michael Marsland contact sheets, 2002-2005 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Images donated by Mack Caldwell ('69), Brinkley Thorne ('72), Wendy Westfall Franzen ('82)Kevin Lichten ('77), Charles Loomis ('85), 1969-1985 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Models, construction, reception, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Slides, 1966-1999 (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Slides, 1967-2000 (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - Construction at various sites, circa 1980s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Mounted exhibit photographs, circa 1990s (Box 3)
  - Photographs, circa 1996 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Plans, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Electronic records
    - Master files used to create The Yale Building Project: The First 40 Years, by Richard W. Hayes
      - Essay - "Learning, Building", 36 computer files (14 TIFF files, 21 JPEG files, 1 DOC file)
        General note
        Contact Public Services (phone: 203 432-1735, e-mail: mssa.reference@yale.edu) for information on accessing this digital object.
      - Essay - "Thirty-Five Years of Teaching Yale Students to Build", 9 computer files (2 TIFF files, 6 JPEG files, 1 DOC file)
      - Essay - "From Appalachia to New Haven", 11 computer files (4 TIFF files, 5 JPEG files, 1 DOC file, 1 GIF file)
      - The Yale Building Project 1967 - 2006, 237 computer files (80 TIFF files, 156 JPEG files, 1 PDF file)
      - Non Image Files, 1793 computer files (238 TIFF files, 1445 JPEG files, 47 PDF files, 20 DWG files, 27 PSD files, 1 DOC file, 15 XLS files)
    - Yale Building Project Digital Archive
      - Camp Farnam Cabin, 1965; 40 computer files (TIFF)
      - New Zion Community Center, 1967; 39 computer files (26 TIFF files, 13 JPEG files)
      - Lower Grassy Community Center, 1968; 49 computer files (44 TIFF files, 5 JPEG files)
      - A Play Machine, 1969; 43 computer files (JPEG)
      - Recreation Center, 1969; 61 computer files (2 TIFF files, 58 JPEG files)
      - New Hampshire Cabins, 1970; 22 computer files (1 TIFF file, 21 JPEG files)
      - Guilford Beach Shelter, 1971; 38 computer files (13 TIFF files, 25 JPEG files)
      - Wallingford Train Station, 1972; 47 computer files (1 TIFF file, 46 JPEG files)
      - Camp Farnam Pavilion, 1973; 28 computer files (2 TIFF files, 26 JPEG files)
      - Playground, 1974; 21 computer files (JPEG)
      - Theater, Fireplace, 1974; 80 computer files (1 TIFF file, 79 JPEG files)
      - Medical Center, 1975; 56 computer files (27 TIFF files, 28 JPEG files)
      - Camp Farnam cabins, 1976; 29 computer files (10 TIFF files, 19 JPEG files)
      - Camp Laurelwood, 1977; 39 computer files (16 TIFF files, 23 JPEG files)
      - Shakespeare Theater, 1978; 52 computer files (34 TIFF files, 18 JPEG files)
      - West Haven Community Center, 1979; 62 computer files (23 TIFF files, 39 JPEG files)
      - Dormitory and Conference Center, 1980; 25 computer files (3 TIFF files, 22 JPEG files)
      - Park Pavilion - East Lyme, 1981; 35 computer files (21 TIFF files, 14 JPEG files)
      - Beach Pavilion and Changing Rooms, 1982; 26 computer files (4 TIFF files, 19 JPEG files, 3 PDF files)
      - Concert Stage - New Haven, 1983; 17 computer files (4 TIFF files, 13 JPEG files)
      - Picnic Pavilion - Lighthouse Point, 1984; 22 computer files (9 TIFF files, 13 JPEG files)
      - Park Pavilioin, East Rock, 1985; 15 computer files (2 TIFF files, 13 JPEG files)
      - Education Pavilion, 1986; 42 computer files (37 TIFF files, 5 JPEG files)
      - Concert Pavilion - Bridgeport, 1987; 35 computer files (9 TIFF files, 26 JPEG files)
      - Meeting House, 1988; 13 computer files (1 TIFF file, 12 JPEG files)
      - Hallock Avenue, 1989; 30 computer files (6 TIFF files, 24 JPEG files)
      - 133 Rosette Street, 1990; 33 computer files (15 TIFF files, 18 JPEG files)
      - Blake Street, 1991; 50 computer files (46 TIFF files, 4 JPEG files)
      - 316 Newhall Street, 1992; 49 computer files (21 TIFF files, 28 JPEG files)
      - 348 Newhall Street, 1993; 65 computer files (37 TIFF files, 28 JPEG files)
      - Dewitt Street, 1994; 60 computer files (18 TIFF files, 42 JPEG files)
      - Cassius Street, 1995; 57 computer files (22 TIFF files, 35 JPEG files)
      - 140 Cedar Hill Avenue, 1996; 34 computer files (5 TIFF files, 29 JPEG files)
      - 50 Derby Avenue, 1997; 28 computer files (7 TIFF files, 21 JPEG files)
      - 96 Sherman Avenue, 1998; 72 computer files (54 TIFF files, 18 JPEG files)
      - 212 Winthrop Avenue, 1999; 51 computer files (6 TIFF files, 45 JPEG files)
      - 23 West Read Street, 2000; 77 computer files (45 TIFF files, 32 JPEG files)
      - 33-35 Fifth Street, 2001; 109 computer files (5 TIFF files, 104 JPEG files)
      - 83 Parmalee Avenue, 2002; 120 computer files (100 JPEG files, 20 DWG files)
      - 14 Porter Street, 2003; 307 computer files (JPEG)
      - 20 Hudson Street, 2004; 374 computer files (369 JPEG files, 1 PDF file, 4 PSD files)
      - 590 Orchard Street, 2005; 375 computer files (1 TIFF file, 372 JPEG files, 2 PSD files)
      - 51 Henry Street, 2006; 270 computer files (JPEG files)
      - New Digital Material, 507 computer files (TIFF)
      - Unknown, 338 computer files (57 TIFF files, 279 JPEG files, 2 DOC files)
- Records, Accession 2010-A-073; 13.5
  - Background material
    - The Building Project-Submission: ACSA Collaborative Practice Award (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - News clippings/press, circa 1982-2003 (Box 1, Folder 2-3)
    - Habitat for Humanity publicity, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Arch 502B, Neighborhood Study Project: Newhallville essays, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Structural calculations: Beach Pavilion, Lighthouse Point Park, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, slides, negatives, and videos
    - Team pictures (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Dock and floating sculptures (Whitesburg, Kentucky); play device, Camp Cedarcrest (Orange, Connecticut); Community Center, Long River Village (Middletown, Connecticut), 1969 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Cabin Creek Medical Center (Dawes, West Virginia); House addition (Branford, Connecticut), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Three cabins at Camp Farnam, Durham, Connecticut, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Camp Laurelwood shelter, Madison, Connecticut, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Picnic pavilion at the Stratford Festival Theatre, Stratford, Connecticut, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
    - West Haven Community House, West Haven, Connecticut, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Cohen Memorial Lodge at Camp Sequassen, New Hartford, Connecticut, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Hopkins pavilion at the Yale Outdoor Education Center, East Lyme, Connecticut, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Beach pavilion and changing rooms, Madison, Connecticut, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Summer concert stage, New Haven, Connecticut, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
    - Two-family house, 63-65 Hallock Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Two-family house, 133 Rosette Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Two-family house, Blake Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - House at 316 Newhall Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - House at 348 Newhall Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 24-25)
    - House at 92 Dewitt Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - House at 10 Cassius Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 27-29)
    - House at 136 Cedar Hill Avenue, New Haven, Connecticut, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - House at 50 Derby Avenue, New Haven, Connecticut, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - House at 96 Sherman Avenue, New Haven, Connecticut, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    - House at 212 Withrop Avenue, New Haven, Connecticut, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - House at 23 West Read Street, New Havent, Connecticut, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    - House at 33 Fifth Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    - The Barn: A Film, videorecording, 1988; 1 (Box 8)
    - Building Project 2002 Contruction, videorecording, 1 (Box 9)
  - Architectural drawings
    - Camp Laurelwood Shelter, Madison, Connecticut, 1977 (Box 4)
    - West Haven Community House, West Haven, Connecticut, 1979 (Box 4)
    - Summer Concert Stage, New Haven, Connecticut, 1983 (Box 4)
    - Picnic Pavilion in Lighthouse Point Park, New Haven, Connecticut, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Seaside Park Bandshell, Bridgeport, Connecticut, 1987
    - Meeting Hall, Smith-Harris Farm, Village of Niantic, Connecticut, 1988 (Box 5)
    - Two-family house, 63-65 Hallock Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 1989 (Box 6)
    - Two-family house, 133 Rosette Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 1990
    - Two-family house, Blake Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 1991 (Box 6)
    - House at 136 Cedar Hill Avenue, New Haven, Connecticut, 1996 (Box 7)
    - House at 50 Derby Avenue, New Haven, Connecticut, 1997 (Box 7)
    - House at 96 Sherman Avenue, New Haven, Connecticut, 1998 (Box 7)
    - House at 212 Withrop Avenue, New Haven, Connecticut, 1999 (Box 7)
    - House at 23 West Read Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 2000 (Box 7)
    - House at 33 Fifth Street, New Haven, Connecticut, 2001 (Box 7)
    - 2003 Building Project Digital Archive, 2002; 144; (121 DWG, 4 DOC, 2 TIF, 17 other)
    - 2004 Building Project Digital Archive, 2003-2004; 8999; (6149 JPG, 830 DWG, 479 TXT, 249 PDF, 174 GIF, 111 TIF, 41 DOC, 966 other files)
    - 2006 Building Project Digital Archive, 2005-2006
  - Computer files (Box 8–18)
    Original born digital files, as well as preservation masters, may not be accessed due to their fragility. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist request that they be made. Born digital files cannot be accessed remotely. System requirements include a Manuscripts and Archives computer and file viewing software.